Finding Aid for the Barbara and Willard Morgan photographs and papers LSC.2278
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Series 10: Barbara Morgan drawings, paintings, and prints, circa 1900s-1960s
  Box 446: Drawings and paintings - (23 x 29 inches and smaller)
  - Subseries 10.1: Drawings, 2 document boxes (397 and 398) and 11 oversize flat boxes (399-404, 406, 408, 445-447), measuring from 12 x 15 to 26 x 37 inches. The artworks vary in size. The dimensions in parentheses below indicate the box size, or maximum size of artworks found in each box.
    Drawings and sketches in graphite, charcoal, pastel, watercolor and ink.
    - Drawings - (10 x 14 inches and smaller) (Box 397, Box 398)
      Box 397 includes drawings, sketches and early childhood collages.
      Box 398 includes paintings, drawings and sketches, 1906-1957; and "Improvisations" 1929-1961, and undated.
    - Drawings - (12 x 15 inches and smaller) (Box 399, Box 400)
    - Drawings - (14 x 16 inches and smaller) (Box 401, Box 402, Box 403)
    - Drawings - (15 x 19 inches and smaller) (Box 196)
      Box 196, folder 8 contains a graphite drawing on paper by Barbara Morgan, Baby Douglas O. Morgan, undated. The paper is fragile and torn.
      Box 196, folder 9 contains The Diary of Fishhooks, 1914, written and illustrated by Barbara Johnson.
    - Drawings - (16 x 20 inches and smaller) (Box 404)
    - Drawings - (19 x 25 inches and smaller) (Box 406, Box 445)
    - Drawings - (23 x 29 inches and smaller) (Box 408, Box 446)
    - Drawings - (26 x 37 inches and smaller) (Box 447)
  - Subseries 10.2: Paintings
    Paintings on paper, board and canvas.
    - Paintings - (10 x 14 inches and smaller) (Box 397, Box 398)
    - Paintings - (12 x 15 inches and smaller) (Box 399, Box 400)
    - Paintings - (14 x 16 inches and smaller) (Box 401, Box 402, Box 403)
    - Paintings - (16 x 20 inches and smaller) (Box 404, Box 405)
    - Paintings - (19 x 25 inches and smaller) (Box 407, Box 445)
    - Paintings - (23 x 29 inches and smaller) (Box 408, Box 446)
    - Paintings - (25 x 31 inches and smaller) (Box 409)
    - Paintings - (26 x 37 inches and smaller) (Box 447)
  - Subseries 10.3: Prints, 1 document box (Box 398) containing works 8 x 10 inches and smalller, and 11 oversize flat boxes (196, 399-400, 402-404, 407, 409, 444, 447), measuring from 12 x 15 to 26 x 37 inches. The artworks vary in size. The dimensions in parentheses below indicate the box size, or maximum size of artworks found in each box.
    Prints on paper.
    - Prints - small (10 x 14 inches and smaller) (Box 398)
    - Prints - (12 x 15 inches and smaller) (Box 399, Box 400)
    - Prints - (14 x 16 inches and smaller) (Box 402, Box 403)
    - Prints - (15 x 19 inches and smaller) (Box 196)
      Box 196 contains 2 copies of Block Prints, a limited edition portfolio of works by UCLA students in the 1930 UCLA block printing class taught by Barbara Morgan, measuring (16 x 11-1/2 inches), and an advertisement in The Daily Bruin for the sale of this limited edition, run of 500. There are also original woodblock prints by Barbara Morgan: "Katchina Dancers" 1929, and "Deer" 1929, and one copy of "Martha Graham" published in Norte Revista Continental Enero, 1942, pp. 32-33 with photographs by Barbara Morgan of Martha Graham and Group.
    - Prints - (16 x 20 inches and smaller) (Box 404)
    - Prints - (17 x 21 inches and smaller) (Box 444)
    - Prints - (19 x 25 inches and smaller) (Box 407)
    - Prints - (25 x 31 inches and smaller) (Box 409)
    - Prints - (26 x 37 inches and smaller) (Box 447)
  - Subseries 10.4: Other media, Contains mixed media artworks, empty portfolios belonging to Barbara Morgan, and journals collected by the Morgan's, including some illustrated by Barbara Morgan. Also includes negatives and transparencies of artworks by Barbara Morgan.
    - Other media - (15 x 19 inches and smaller) (Box 196)
      Box 196 contains two empty portfolios belonging to Barbara Morgan, one with label and logo of Arthur Wesley Dow Association, and the other with handwritten label, "To / California - 1930 / Mono Lake, etc."
      Also included are two oversize journals focused on war, U.S.S.R. in Construction, No. 19, 1938; and S. Paulo, No. 9; and a photocopy of Terrell, Robert, "Hearst is Still Alive!" in New Masses, June 13, 1939 (Vol. 31, No. 12) with illustrations by William Randolph Hearst, and photomontage by Barbara Morgan, "Hearst Over the People".
    - Other media - (12 x 15 inches and smaller) (Box 397, Box 398)
    - Other media - negatives and transparencies of artworks, 1 document box. (Box 595)
      Includes negatives and transparencies of artworks by Barbara Morgan.
- Series 11: Barbara Morgan subject files, 1930s-2000s
  This series contains reference material collected by Morgan, including books, catalogs, journals, clippings, flyers, and ephemera. Art and photography material is primarily related to galleries and institutions; dance material is related to individual dancers, including Martha Graham, Erick Hawkins, Pearl Primus, and José Limón.
  Other subject files consist of clippings, ephemera, and published material on history, culture, philosophy, and politics. The majority of this material is from the 1960s-1970s, reflecting Morgan's interests and projects during that period. This series also includes Morgan's notes and correspondence regarding her research.
  - Art, 1930s-2000s (Box 136, Box 137, Box 138)
  - Dance, 1930s-2000s (Box 139, Box 140)
  - Photography, 1940s-1990s (Box 141)
  - Indians (Native Americans), 1960s-1970s (Box 142, Box 143)
  - Pictographs, 1960s-1980s (Box 143, Box 144)
  - Archaeology, anthropology, 1960s-1970s (Box 144)
  - Tibet, other countries, 1960s-1970s (Box 145)
  - Politics, philosophy, undated (Box 146, Box 147, Box 148)
  - Reference books, undated (Box 190, Box 191, Box 192)
- Series 12: Willard Morgan photography career, 1922-1994; 1930-1967
  This series contains material related to Willard Morgan's career as a professional photographer, including his employment at E. Leitz, Inc. and Leica Camera (1930-1936), Life magazine (1936-1938), MoMA (1943-1944), and Look magazine (1944-1945). The series also includes material related to lectures and presentations Morgan gave on the subject of photography; records of his involvement in photography exhibitions; and his participation in professional photography organizations and conferences, including the Circle of Confusion photography group. Other documents include correspondence, receipts, reference materials, business letterhead, and notes.
  See also Series 17: Willard Morgan working files, 1930s-1960s.
  - Subseries 12.1: E. Leitz, Inc. and Leica Camera, 1928-1994
    This subseries contains documentation of Willard Morgan's employment by E. Leitz, Inc., where he served as manager of the Leica Sales Promotions, and Photo-Optical departments from 1930-1936. Included are correspondence, lecture materials, newsletters, equipment catalogs, instruction manuals, product photographs, and exhibition catalogs primarily related to Morgan's work with the Leica product line.
    - Correspondence, 1930-1937, 1962-1964 (Box 102, Folder 1)
    - Edward A. Hill correspondence, 1950 (Box 102, Folder 2)
    - Leica demonstration and lecture materials, 1930-1931 (Box 102, Folder 3)
    - Leica product photographs, circa 1932 (Box 102, Folder 4)
    - Leica manuals, 1928-1969 (Box 220, Folders 1-5, Box 221, Folders 1-2)
    - Leica Fotografie magazines, 1953 (Box 220, Folder 6)
    - Leica promotional material, circa 1990s (Box 220, Folder 7)
    - Leica price list, 1953 (Box 220, Folder 8)
    - Zone System publications, 1956-1968 (Box 221, Folder 3)
    - Various manuals, 1952-1960 (Box 221, Folder 4)
    - Morgan instruction manuals, 1959 (Box 221, Folder 5)
    - Leitz and Leica product catalogs, 1930-1937 (Box 102, Folder 5)
    - Leica Dealers' Bulletin, 1932-1935 (Box 102, Folder 6)
    - Leica Photography newsletter, 1932-1933 (Box 102, Folder 7)
    - Leica Photography magazines, 1939-1954 (Box 102, Folder 8)
    - Leica technical information, 1933 (Box 103, Folder 1)
    - Leica publication publicity, 1932-1935 (Box 103, Folder 2)
    - Leica dealer catalog, 1966 (Box 103, Folder 3)
    - Translation from Die Geschicte der Kleinbildkamera bis zur Leica, 1960 (Box 103, Folder 4)
    - Leica exhibition catalogs, 1936-1937, 1994 (Box 103, Folders 5-8, Box 182, Folder 6)
    - Photographs by Willard Morgan (Box 607, Folder 10)
      Box 607, folder 10 includes two photographs by Willard Morgan: a 1937 print of Alfred Eisenstaedt with his Leica camera, and an 8 x 10 print of a dirigible with Nazi insignia, and an unattributed photograph of a "Stamp Out Fascism" poster.
      Box 607, folder 13 includes a negative of designers John Weber and Eleanor LeMaire and negatives of swimmers.
  - Subseries 12.2: MoMA, 1939-1989
    This subseries relates to Willard Morgan's employment as MoMA's first Director of the Department of Photography and the Photography Center. It includes correspondence, meeting minutes, and reports from the Advisory Committee on Photography; Morgan's 1943 personal work journal; photographs of Willard and Barbara at the Museum; and publicity related to MoMA and its Photography Center.
    - Correspondence, 1943-1944 (Box 104, Folder 1)
    - Advisory Committee on Photography, 1943-1945 (Box 104, Folder 2)
    - Journal and photographs, 1943-1944 (Box 104, Folder 3)
    - Photography Center publicity, 1943, 1989 (Box 104, Folder 4)
    - American Snapshot exhibition, 1944 (Box 104, Folder 5)
    - Exhibition publicity, 1939-1963 (Box 104, Folder 6, Box 607, Folder 11)
  - Subseries 12.3: Photography exhibitions, 1938-1993
    This subseries contains material relating to Willard Morgan's involvement in various photographic exhibitions, primarily the First International Photographic Exposition, held in 1938, which included the first exhibition of Farm Security Administration (FSA) photographs. Materials consist of participation badges, invitations, notes, travel documents, stock certificates, photographs, press releases, rules and regulations, publicity, exhibition lists, and correspondence. Letters from Roy E. Stryker, Chief of the Historical Section of the Division of Information under the United States Department of Agriculture, make up the bulk of the correspondence. Also included are materials from the Fifth International Salon of the Pictorial Photographers of America and the 1936 U.S. Camera Photography Exhibition.
    - First International Photographic Exposition - planning and participation documentation, 1938 (Box 104, Folder 7)
    - First International Photographic Exposition - photographs and publicity, 1938 (Box 104, Folder 8)
    - First International Photographic Exposition - FSA exhibition correspondence, 1938-1941, 1962-1965, 1993 (Box 104, Folders 9-10)
    - Fifth International Salon of the Pictorial Photographers of America, 1938 (Box 104, Folder 11)
    - U.S. Camera photography exhibition, 1936 (Box 104, Folder 12)
  - Subseries 12.4: Photography lectures, 1932-1947
    This subseries contains material relating to Willard Morgan's non-Leica lectures between 1932 and 1947. Materials include correspondence; lecture notes, notecards and drafts; biographical sketches; travel documents; conference proceedings; reference materials, including newspaper clippings and articles; lecture publicity, such as press releases and newspaper advertisements; and response letters from his lectures at the Eighth International Salon of Nature Photography, the 10th and 17th annual conventions of the Master Photo Finishers of America, and other meetings.
    - Eighth International Salon of Nature Photography, 1946 (Box 105, Folder 1)
    - Brooklyn Institute of Arts and Sciences, 1945-1946 (Box 105, Folder 2)
    - Camera Club New York, 1945 (Box 105, Folder 3)
    - Master Photo Finishers of America conference presentations, 1932, 1939 (Box 105, Folder 4)
    - Other lecture materials, 1939-1947 (Box 105, Folder 5)
    - Lecture notes and reference materials, 1937-1947 (Box 105, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 12.5: Circle of Confusion, 1936, 1945-1968
    This subseries contains correspondence, membership lists, negatives, and photographs related to the Circle of Confusion professional photography group.
    - Correspondence and membership lists, 1945-1968 (Box 105, Folder 7)
    - Photographic prints and negatives, circa 1936 (Box 105, Folders 8-10, Box 607, Folder 12)
  - Subseries 12.6: Other photography career materials, 1922-1978
    This subseries primarily contains correspondence, memos, reports, photographs, newsletters, and notecards related to WIllard Morgan's employment at Life magazine and Look magazine. There is also other professional correspondence, membership and meeting attendance documentation, notes, receipts, letterhead, and reference materials from Morgan's career as a photographer. Also included are plans, correspondence, and photographs related to a 1962 Farm Security Administration reunion party hosted by the Morgans at their home (see also Subseries 19.4: Family photographic material, circa 1850s-1990s).
    - Life magazine, 1937-1939, 1978 (Box 106, Folder 1)
    - Look magazine, 1944-1945 (Box 106, Folder 2)
    - Photography correspondence, 1945-1967 (Box 106, Folder 3)
    - Eastman Kodak correspondence and reference materials, 1922-1967 (Box 106, Folder 4)
    - Photographic professional organization materials, 1934-1935, 1965-1967 (Box 106, Folder 5)
    - Receipts, notes, reference materials, 1938-1966 (Box 106, Folder 6)
    - Business letterhead, circa 1920s, 1950s (Box 106, Folder 7)
    - Second National Training Conference of the National Defense Executive Reserve, 1960 (Box 106, Folder 8)
    - Farm Security Administration party - plans, correspondence, photographs, 1962 (Box 216, Folder 9)
      Party photographer: Pancho Tremaine.
    - Farm Security Administration party - negatives, 1962 (Box 608, Folder 21)
- Series 13: Willard Morgan writings and published materials, 1901-1950; 1926-1947
  Willard Morgan was involved in a variety of writing and publishing projects over the course of his career, although the majority of his writing concerned photography-related subjects. One of his largest projects was editing The Complete Photographer, an encyclopedic serial publication published by the National Educational Alliance, between 1941 and 1944. Other writings include personal inventions, encyclopedia entries, and a series of articles titled What Every Salesman Should Know, written for Photographic Retailing.
  Willard Morgan writings and published materials are also found in Series 14: Willard Morgan architecture photography and projects; Series 18: Collaborative work; and Series 20: Publishing company materials.
  - Subseries 13.1: The Complete Photographer, 1901-1944; 1941-1944
    This subseries contains material related to Willard Morgan's encyclopedic publication, The Complete Photographer. Materials include advertisements, correspondence, reference materials, and bound and individual issues. See also Series 17: Willard Morgan working files for additional material generated from and used in this publication.
    - Advertisements, circa 1941 (Box 107, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1941-1944 (Box 107, Folder 2)
    - Index of photographs and articles, 1941-1943 (Box 107, Folder 3)
    - National Aeronautics Council test mailings, circa 1941 (Box 107, Folder 4)
    - Sample advertising materials, circa 1941 (Box 107, Folder 5)
    - Bound index, 1943 (Box 107, Folder 8)
    - Bound issues, 1941-1943 (Box 107, Folders 6-7, Box 108, Box 109, Box 110)
    - Individual issues, 1941-1944 (Box 110, Box 222, Box 223, Box 224)
    - Camera Journalism with the Miniature Camera, 1936 (Box 112, Folder 7)
    - Photo-Miniature magazine, 1901-1932 (Box 111, Box 112, Box 225)
  - Subseries 13.2: Other written and published materials, 1926-1950; 1940-1947
    This subseries contains other materials authored by Willard Morgan, such as his work on the Ten Eventful Years article he wrote for the Encyclopedia Britannica, schematics and summaries of Willard's personal inventions, booklets he published through the National Educational Alliance, a series of articles titled What Every Salesman Should Know, which he wrote for Photographic Retailing, and other published and unpublished materials.
    - Encyclopedia Britannica correspondence and article drafts, 1946-1947 (Box 113, Folder 1)
    - Encyclopedia Britannica reference materials, 1933-1946 (Box 113, Folder 2)
    - Inventions, circa 1926 (Box 113, Folder 3)
    - National Educational Alliance, Inc. instruction manuals, 1941-1947 (Box 113, Folders 4-6)
    - Published photography articles, 1929-1950 (Box 113, Folder 7, Box 409, Folder 6, Box 439, Folder 4)
    - What Every Salesman Should Know, 1939-1940 (Box 113, Folder 8)
    - Other published articles, 1927-1929 (Box 113, Folder 9)
    - Unpublished articles, 1926, 1940-1945 (Box 113, Folder 10)
- Series 14: Willard Morgan architectural photography and projects, 1925-2010; 1925-1930
  This series contains Willard Morgan's photographic and written work regarding architecture. Materials include correspondence, photographic prints, negatives, architectural sketches and plans, drafts and published articles, press releases, books, and notes.
  Starting in the mid-1920s, Morgan began photographing buildings in the Los Angeles area. Many of his images depict structures designed by Richard Neutra and Frank Lloyd Wright. He eventually developed a close and long-lasting friendship with Neutra and the two united on several collaborative projects, including Neutra's book, Richard Neutra on Building: Mystery and Realities of the Site, published by Morgan & Morgan (See Series 20: Publishing company materials). Morgan also had a professional relationship with Frank Lloyd Wright, photographing his work in Los Angeles and Chicago. He photographed works of other architects in Los Angeles, including Alexander Brandner, Irving Gill, Julius Ralph Davidson, and Rudolph Schindler.
  Morgan's prints, negatives, and published articles related to drive-in markets are also included in the series. Toward the end of the 1920s, Morgan became interested in drive-in markets, which were a relatively new concept at the time. Similar to modern-day strip malls, they allowed shoppers to conveniently park their cars near the stores.
  - Subseries 14.1: Richard Neutra, 1925-2010; 1925-1930
    This subseries includes a large number of Willard Morgan's prints and negatives of Richard Neutra's work in Southern California, such as the Jardinette Apartments, Lovell Physical Culture Center, and Lovell Health House. Also included is correspondence between the Morgans and Neutras, original Neutra drawings, articles written by and about Neutra, and articles written by Willard Morgan.
    See also Box 273 for contact prints of Richard Neutra and Frank Lloyd Wright works; and Boxes 282 and 283 for lantern slides of Neutra, Sullivan and Wright works.
    Boxes 114, 115 and 116 contain negatives and prints of Richard Neutra and Frank Lloyd Wright works.
    - Barnsdall House wading pool, circa 1925 (Box 114, Folder 1)
    - Conrad Buff House garage, circa 1925 (Box 114, Folder 2)
    - Jardinette Apartments, circa 1928 (Box 114, Folder 3)
    - Lovell Health House - architectural plans and sketches, 1926-1928 (Box 114, Folder 4)
    - Lovell Health House - construction photographs, circa 1927 (Box 114, Folder 5)
    - Lovell Health House - exterior photographs, circa 1929 (Box 114, Folder 6)
    - Lovell Health House - interior photographs, circa 1930 (Box 114, Folder 7)
    - Lovell Health House - Willard Morgan correspondence and written materials, 1928-1930, 2010 (Box 115, Folder 1)
    - Lovell Physical Culture Center, circa 1927 (Box 115, Folder 2)
    - Architectural plans and drawings, 1929-1944 (Box 115, Folder 3)
    - Furniture and lighting, circa 1925 (Box 115, Folder 4)
    - Photographs and images of Richard Neutra, circa 1930 (Box 115, Folder 5)
    - Photographs from Wie Baut Amerika?, circa 1927 (Box 115, Folder 6)
    - Written materials about the Neutras, 1944-1999 (Box 115, Folder 7)
    - Written materials by Richard Neutra, 1927-1951 (Box 115, Folder 8)
    - Modern architecture book project, circa 1925 (Box 115, Folder 9)
    - Richard Neutra architectural sketches, circa 1929 (Box 117, Folder 13)
  - Subseries 14.2: Frank Lloyd Wright, 1930-1994
    This subseries contains negatives and prints of Frank Lloyd Wright's Aline Barnsdall Hollyhock House, Samuel Freeman House, Unity Temple, and other structures; photographs of Wright's John Sowden House; and correspondence, photography catalogs, and written materials about Wright's architecture.
    For contact prints of Richard Neutra and Frank Lloyd Wright works, see Box 273.
    For lantern slides of Neutra, Sullivan and Wright works, see Boxes 282 and 283.
    - Aline Barnsdall Hollyhock House, circa 1931 (Box 116, Folder 1, Box 189, Box 429)
      5 x 7 prints in box 429, folder 2 are unattributed, possibly photographed by Barbara Morgan.
    - Arthur Heurtley House, circa 1930 (Box 116, Folder 2)
    - Frederick C. Robie House, circa 1930 (Box 116, Folder 3)
    - Samuel Freeman House, circa 1930 (Box 116, Folder 4)
    - Unity Temple, circa 1930 (Box 116, Folder 5)
    - Unidentified, circa 1920s (Box 116, Folder 6)
    - Lloyd Wright - John Sowden House, circa 1927 (Box 116, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1932 (Box 116, Folder 8)
    - Inquiries and information about photographs, 1940, 1990-1994 (Box 116, Folder 9)
  - Subseries 14.3: Louis Sullivan, circa 1930
    This subseries contains prints, negatives, and inventory lists of Willard Morgan's photography of the Louis Sullivan-designed Wainwright Building and Wainwright Tomb, both located in St. Louis, Missouri.
    - Wainwright Building, circa 1930 (Box 116, Folder 10)
    - Wainwright Tomb, circa 1930 (Box 116, Folder 11)
    - Lists of architectural works and related photographs, circa 1930 (Box 116, Folder 12)
  - Subseries 14.4: Los Angeles architecture, 1926-1929
    This subseries contains prints and negatives of Willard Morgan's photography of architectural structures in Los Angeles, including the Bullocks Wilshire, James Oviatt, and Title Insurance buildings. This subseries also includes images depicting the work of architects Alexander Brandner, Irving Gill, Julius Ralph Davidson, and Rudolph Schindler.
    - Alexander Brandner - Luther Burbank Middle School, circa 1926 (Box 117, Folder 1)
    - Bullocks Wilshire building, circa 1929 (Box 117, Folder 2)
    - Industrial buildings and landscapes, circa 1925 (Box 117, Folder 3)
    - Irving Gill, circa 1925 (Box 117, Folder 4)
    - James Oviatt building, circa 1928 (Box 117, Folder 5)
    - Julius Ralph Davidson - Wilshire Boulevard shops, circa 1929-1930 (Box 117, Folder 6, Box 409, Folder 5)
    - Rudolph Schindler - Lovell Beach House, circa 1926 (Box 117, Folder 7)
    - Title Insurance building, circa 1928 (Box 117, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 14.5: Drive-in markets, 1928-1930
    This subseries includes Willard Morgan's prints, negatives, and published articles related to Los Angeles-area drive-in markets, including photographs of Richard Neutra sketches for storefronts. The markets photographed include the Mesa Vernon, Palm, El Adobe, Sunset-Western, Fountain, LA Motor In, Beverly-La Brea Motor In, La Cesta, and Mandarin stores in Los Angeles.
    - Mesa Vernon Market, circa 1928 (Box 117, Folder 9)
    - Palm Market, circa 1928 (Box 117, Folder 10)
    - Other drive-in markets, circa 1928 (Box 117, Folder 11)
    - Unidentified drive-in markets, circa 1928 (Box 117, Folder 12)
    - Chain Store Review articles, 1928-1930 (Box 117, Folder 14)
    - Tiles and Tile Work articles, 1929-1930 (Box 117, Folder 15)